<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Abel Soares Siqueira</title>
        <link>https://abelsiqueira.github.io/tag/code/feed.xml</link>
        <description>RSS feed for abelsiqueira.github.io</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2022 06:56:11 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/nuxt-community/feed-module</generator>
        <category>Nuxt.js</category>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Advent of Code 2016 in Julia]]></title>
            <link>https://abelsiqueira.github.io/blog/2016-12-18-advent-of-code-2016-in-julia</link>
            <guid>https://abelsiqueira.github.io/blog/2016-12-18-advent-of-code-2016-in-julia</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 18 Dec 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
# Advent of Code 2016 in Julia

Last year I discovered by chance a code competition that happens in the month
of December: The [Advent of Code](http://adventofcode.com).
This event consists of small puzzles release every day of December, up to the
25th. Which amounts to 25 problems! (I can do math).

Last year I tried doing some on Bash, and latter switched to Julia, but never
got to finish them.
This year I decided to use [Julia](https://julialang.org), because I want to
test it for these general problems. Some problems are very hard, and I want
to have the packages at my disposal.

**There is a leaderboard**, which revolves around the first 100 solvers for
each day. Most problems are solved in the first 5 minutes of its release, and
the 100th place is usually less than 15 minutes. The best I got was 30 minutes,
getting the 135th position and zero points. However, I'm usually not trying to
get there because the problems are release at 3am for me (Brazil), and by that
time I'm usually sleeping.

This year I'm trying to follow more closely the dates, managed to solve one by
day until a gigantic workload halted my progress for a week. Yesterday I
returned to these problems and solved the missing ones up until now.

If you like coding, you should give it a try. My code for this year is
available at [GitHub](https://github.com/abelsiqueira/AoC2016), but only open
it if you decided not to play. Be warned that most of my answers were poorly
written because I still want to do it fast, and am not worried about cleaning
of efficiency.

Happy new year, holidays, and coding.
]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>