<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Abel Soares Siqueira</title>
        <link>https://abelsiqueira.github.io/tag/life/feed.xml</link>
        <description>RSS feed for abelsiqueira.github.io</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2022 22:06:22 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/nuxt-community/feed-module</generator>
        <category>Nuxt.js</category>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Long time away]]></title>
            <link>https://abelsiqueira.github.io/blog/2016-07-06-long-time-away</link>
            <guid>https://abelsiqueira.github.io/blog/2016-07-06-long-time-away</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
# Long time away

Hello, it's been a long time since my last post, and a lot has
happened since.
I've had difficulty finding time to write a good post, or even a bad
post, sometimes, but now I return with a brief explaining, and some
possible continuation posts.

First, during the classes period, I have a lot of obligations that use
a lot of time: Preparing classes, tests, projects, grading, etc.
This was most of my time.

Additionally, in May, I went to two conferences in my field, the
Optimization Days 2016, in Montreal, Canada, and the XI Brazilian Workshop on
Continuos Optimization, in Manaus/Amazonas, here in Brazil.
For the first, I left at the end of April, but I had no visa, so I had
to rush to get everything in order, then get the tickets and the
hotel, while preparing the talk. I also worked with Dominique Orban in
there, which you should know from CUTEst.

Furthermore, I also gave a talk about Games and Artificial
Intelligence for undergrad students around April and a talk about
Julia for the Informatics grad program around May.

June was a month of closures. I (re)done an old paper with Francisco
Gomes and submitted it. I almost finished the content of a paper with
Geovani Grapiglia. CUTEst (and related) is (are) almost ready for
release. The classes finished.

This week, the first of July, I had the pleasure of having Miles
Lubin, from MIT, over at UFPR. He gave a tutorial on JuMP, presenting
a linear and a non-linear model. People were very interested, and it
was very popular. There were 28 people attending it, with interest
from the audience and a wide range of fields. I do plan to use JuMP in
future classes, and some colleagues might too.
Also this week, there is a Term Paper defense, and the second part of my
tenure-track avaliation.

Now that I'll have more time again, I'll probably make more posts. I
have one about CUTEst, which I expected to make when released, but
maybe I'll have to do earlier to avoid confusion.
I also want to make more applications of mathematics with Julia, but
let's see what happens.

See you soon.
]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>