<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Abel Soares Siqueira</title>
        <link>https://abelsiqueira.github.io/tag/fun/feed.xml</link>
        <description>RSS feed for abelsiqueira.github.io</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Oct 2022 22:59:04 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/nuxt-community/feed-module</generator>
        <category>Nuxt.js</category>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Julia Fractal on Julia]]></title>
            <link>https://abelsiqueira.github.io/blog/2017-01-15-julia-fractal-on-julia</link>
            <guid>https://abelsiqueira.github.io/blog/2017-01-15-julia-fractal-on-julia</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
# Julia Fractal on Julia

I wanted a background that would update automatically in some
interesting way, instead of just random images.
After some thought, I decided to use some [Julia
fractals](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Julia_set).

I made a code to create the Julia fractals in the [Julia
language](https://julialang.org), and then some code to run it for a random
point.

The code is [here](https://github.com/abelsiqueira/juliabg), including some
explaining on how to use and install it.

Here are some examples:

![](https://raw.githubusercontent.com/abelsiqueira/juliabg/master/ex1.png)
![](https://raw.githubusercontent.com/abelsiqueira/juliabg/master/ex2.png)
![](https://raw.githubusercontent.com/abelsiqueira/juliabg/master/ex3.png)
![](https://raw.githubusercontent.com/abelsiqueira/juliabg/master/ex4.png)
]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Advent of Code 2016 in Julia]]></title>
            <link>https://abelsiqueira.github.io/blog/2016-12-18-advent-of-code-2016-in-julia</link>
            <guid>https://abelsiqueira.github.io/blog/2016-12-18-advent-of-code-2016-in-julia</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 18 Dec 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
# Advent of Code 2016 in Julia

Last year I discovered by chance a code competition that happens in the month
of December: The [Advent of Code](http://adventofcode.com).
This event consists of small puzzles release every day of December, up to the
25th. Which amounts to 25 problems! (I can do math).

Last year I tried doing some on Bash, and latter switched to Julia, but never
got to finish them.
This year I decided to use [Julia](https://julialang.org), because I want to
test it for these general problems. Some problems are very hard, and I want
to have the packages at my disposal.

**There is a leaderboard**, which revolves around the first 100 solvers for
each day. Most problems are solved in the first 5 minutes of its release, and
the 100th place is usually less than 15 minutes. The best I got was 30 minutes,
getting the 135th position and zero points. However, I'm usually not trying to
get there because the problems are release at 3am for me (Brazil), and by that
time I'm usually sleeping.

This year I'm trying to follow more closely the dates, managed to solve one by
day until a gigantic workload halted my progress for a week. Yesterday I
returned to these problems and solved the missing ones up until now.

If you like coding, you should give it a try. My code for this year is
available at [GitHub](https://github.com/abelsiqueira/AoC2016), but only open
it if you decided not to play. Be warned that most of my answers were poorly
written because I still want to do it fast, and am not worried about cleaning
of efficiency.

Happy new year, holidays, and coding.
]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[SiCLIPoD - Um Gerenciador de Podcasts Simples em Linha de Comando]]></title>
            <link>https://abelsiqueira.github.io/blog/2014-12-11-siclipod-um-gerenciador-de-podcasts-simples-em-linha-de-comando</link>
            <guid>https://abelsiqueira.github.io/blog/2014-12-11-siclipod-um-gerenciador-de-podcasts-simples-em-linha-de-comando</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2014 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
# SiCLIPoD - Um Gerenciador de Podcasts Simples em Linha de Comando

Há algum tempo eu, esporadicamente, eu escuto o podcast do [Jovem
Nerd](http://jovemnerd.com.br/categoria/nerdcast/).
Mas acessar o site é chato, então eu fui procurar um gerenciador de podcasts.
Não gostei de nenhum (o [gpodder](http://gpodder.org/) quase foi escolhido).
Daí, resolvi cria um no estilo que eu gosto.
Falta MUITO pra ficar bom mas pode ser de alguma utilidade para alguém.
O código está no [GitHub](https://github.com/abelsiqueira/siclipod).
O básico pra funcionar é

```
siclipod add URL
siclipod list
siclipod list NAME
siclipod search NAME STUFF
siclipod download NAME STUFF
siclipod play NAME STUFF
```

O normal é tocar com o `smplayer`,
mas você pode editar `$HOME/.siclipod/.config` para colocar o que quiser.
Nem o README eu completei ainda.
]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Jogos de Tabuleiro]]></title>
            <link>https://abelsiqueira.github.io/blog/2014-06-04-jogos-de-tabuleiro</link>
            <guid>https://abelsiqueira.github.io/blog/2014-06-04-jogos-de-tabuleiro</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2014 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
# Jogos de Tabuleiro

Eu (não tão) recementemente me interessei em jogos de tabuleiro. Para
clarificar, não estou me referindo aos jogos de tabuleiro "clássicos", como War,
Banco Imobiliário, etc.. Estou me referindo aos jogos de tabuleiro com mecânica
avançada. Isso não significa que todos eles são complexos, mas que eles são (em
sua maioria) bem pensados e balanceados.
Esse jogos de tabuleiro juntaram uma legião de seguidores, a maioria geeks e
nerds, que está interessada em algum hobby legal. Note que RPG e jogos digitais
normalmente são parte desses hobbies.
Mais informações podem ser obtidas no ótimo site [board game
geek](http://www.boardgamegeek.com).

Uma das melhoras coisas de jogos de tabuleiros é a grande variedade de
complexidade e seriedade que eles cobrem. Você pode jogar um jogo de 10-15
minutos com regras extremamente simples (como Fluxx), ou um jogo intenso, sem
sorte envolvida, de várias horas (como Diplomacia). Um dos meus jogos favoritos
do momento é Battlestar Galactica, um jogo baseado na série homônima.
]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>